Rose DelMonico Murphy Papers VHP2006/2
CCSU Veterans History Project
Rose DelMonico Murphy Papers
Bulk, 1942-1946
1942 – 1946, 1984, 1994, 2006
VHP2006/2
CCSU Veterans History Project
92.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
The collection details Rose Delmonico Murphy's World War II experience which she served as a nurse in Army hospitals in the South West Pacific, New Zealand, Saipan, Iwo Jima, Okinawa, and New Caledonia
Murphy, Rose DelMonico, 1911 -
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Biographical/Historical note
A New Haven native, Rose Murphy was called to active duty while a Nurse at Yale New Haven Hospital, where she was assigned after graduating from Grace-New Haven School of Nursing in 1933. Captain Murphy served in Army hospitals in the South West Pacific, New Zealand, and Saipan tending soldiers injured in battles on Guadalcanal, Iwo Jima, Okinawa, and New Caledonia. Rose achieved the rank of Captain, and is the proud recipient of the Asiatic Pacific Theatre Campaign Ribbon.
United States. Army Nurse Corps.; United States. Army. 39th General Hospital (Auckland, New Zealand).; Australia; Camp Edwards (Mass.); Guadalcanal (Solomon Islands); Guam; Interviews; Manuscript; New Zealand; Okinawa-shi (Japan); Photographs; Saipan; Tinian (Northern Mariana Islands); World War II - - Personal Narrative, American; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Women; World War, 1939-1945--Hospitals--Pacific Area
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/2.I
  - Rose Delmonico Murphy's Resume, After 1984; VHP2006-02.I.1
  - Certificate of Service, Dec. 26, 1945; VHP2006-02.I.2
  - Military Record and Report of Separation, Dec. 26, 1945; VHP2006-02.I.3
  - Commendation from the White House signed by then President Harry S. Truman, Between 1945 - 1953; VHP2006-02.I.4
  - Pacific Ocean Areas shoulder sleeve insignia(patch), 1944; VHP2006-02.I.5
  - Rose DelMonico's memoirs titled "Rose DelMonico, US. Army Nurse WW II served in southwest Pacific 1942 - 1945", Between 1998 - 2006; VHP2006-02.I.6; 35.0 Digital objects
  - Correspondence from Sergeant Albert Graff to Mrs. Delmonico (Rose’s mother), Jul. 5, 1943; VHP2006-02.I.7; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Calendar of World War II major events, VHP2006-02.I.8; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Rose Delmonico Murphy's interview synopsis, May 11, 2006; VHP2006-02.I.9
- Series II: Publications, VHP2006/2.II
  - "Nurses Sworn In as Second Lieutenants in Army" New Haven Register news article, Mar. 18, 1942; VHP2006/2.II.1
  - Compilation of poems written by various enlisted personnel, Oct. 13, 1942; VHP2006/6.II.2; 3.0 Digital objects
  - "World War II Retrospective" New Haven Register news article, Jul. 30, 1994; VHP2006/6.II.3; 5.0 Digital objects
  - American Nurses Interest in New Life, n.d.; VHP2006/6.II.4
  - Guadalcanal Story told by Father Finnegan, n.d.; VHP2006/6.II.5
  - "Hamden Notables Get Their Moment" Hamden Chronicle article, Apr. 4, 2006; VHP2006/6.II.6; 2.0 Digital objects
  - "Nightingale in Flight" New Haven Register column, Apr. 30, 2006; VHP2006/6.II.7
- Series III: Multi-Media, VHP2006/2.III
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/2.III
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy graduation portrait, 1933; VHP2006/6.III.1
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy graduation photograph, 1933; VHP2006/6.III.2
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy and the Yale Nursing Unit, 1942; VHP2006/6.III.3
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy in New Zealand, 1942; VHP2006/6.III.4
    - 1st Lieutenant Rose Delmonico Murphy on duty in New Zealand., 1942; VHP2006/6.III.5
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy and Irene Carroll in New Zealand, 1942; VHP2006/6.III.6
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy and Irene Carroll in New Zealand, 1942; VHP2006/6.III.7
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy and Irene Carroll in New Zealand, 1942; VHP2006/6.III.8
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy and a group of nurses in New Zealand, 1942; VHP2006/6.III.9
    - Catherine Finegan in New Zealand., 1942; VHP2006/6.III.10
    - Catherine Finegan in New Zealand., 1942; VHP2006/6.III.11
    - Army nurses relaxing in New Zealand, 1942; VHP2006/6.III.12
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy posing in swimsuit in New Zealand., 1942; VHP2006/6.III.13
    - Doctors and nurses in swimsuits on the beach in New Zealand, 1942; VHP2006/6.III.14
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy and Irene Carroll with male companions in New Zealand., 1942; VHP2006/6.III.15
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy and Julie McGrath, 1942; VHP2006/6.III.16
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy and military personnel with native Maori in New Zealand., 1942; VHP2006/6.III.17
    - Maori mother and child in New Zealand, 1942; VHP2006/6.III.18
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy and a group of army nurses with Australian dignitary in New Zealand., 1942; VHP2006/6.III.19
    - Cleaning ladies in New Zealand, 1942; VHP2006/6.III.20
    - Irene Carroll, Doctor Helzaur, and Rose Delmonico Murphy in new Zealand., 1942; VHP2006/6.III.21
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy with other American nurses in evening attire., 1942; VHP2006/6.III.22
    - Portrait of Rose Delmonico Murphy in Saipan after her promotion., 1944; VHP2006/6.III.23
    - Military barracks on Saipan, 1944; VHP2006/6.III.24
    - Painting of Rose Delmonico Murphy, 1944; VHP2006/6.III.25
    - Laundry on Saipan, 1944; VHP2006/6.III.26
    - Esther Budd with unknown nurse in Saipan, 1944; VHP2006/6.III.27
    - Outhouse on Saipan, 1944; VHP2006/6.III.28
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy outside barracks in Saipan., 1944; VHP2006/6.III.29
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy and a group of American nurses having returned to the United States from overseas duty have dinner in California., 1944; VHP2006/6.III.30
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy at her home during oral history interview., 2006; VHP2006/6.III.31
    - Rose Delmonico Murphy at her home during oral history interview., 2006; VHP2006/6.III.32
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/2.IIIb
    - Oral history interview, VHP2006/2.IIIb.1; 1.0 dvd (Disk DVD VHP2006/2, Box VHP Interview 2006)